<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>nlm&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://nlm.github.io/blog/tags/artificial-intelligence/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on nlm&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://nlm.github.io/blog/tags/artificial-intelligence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A thought on autonomous cars</title>
      <link>https://nlm.github.io/blog/2016/12/a-thought-on-autonomous-cars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 23:43:44 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nlm.github.io/blog/2016/12/a-thought-on-autonomous-cars/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In a time where the first autonomous cars are hitting the road,
new questions emerge on the behaviour and responsabilities of
the artificial intelligence running these.
&lt;!-- more /--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-controversy-about-autonomous-vehicles&#34;&gt;The controversy about autonomous vehicles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve read a bit about this subject in the news lately. There is
a contronversy on either it&amp;rsquo;ll be a good or bad thing to have
autonomous cars on the streets. The main concern is where goes
the responsability when something goes wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to say that i&amp;rsquo;m sure it&amp;rsquo;ll probably be a good thing overall.
But it will probably go through a lot of scepticism and criticism
in the beginning, even fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it&amp;rsquo;ll make people afraid. Every accident involving these vehicles
will have thousands of times more publicity than any other accident.
So, of course, it&amp;rsquo;ll probably get a bad reputation. Inevitably, some bugs
will be present, and cause problems too, worsening the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, there will be the problem of human jobs replacement. When you hire
a man to drive a truck, there is a whole lot of laws and regulations that
you have to obey. You have to pay a salary, deal with the sickness, insurances,
working time, mandatory breaks, nights of sleep, vacations, unions, complaints.
A whole lot of stuff that does not apply to robots.  So some people won&amp;rsquo;t
like that, because it means a lot of people losing their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will probably be the biggest problem here. For now there is no solution for
large scale unemployment in this area, so this will be forbidden or limited
by laws, using the argument of road safety to prevent these cars to be fully
autonomous and requiring an operator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-matter-of-responsability&#34;&gt;A matter of responsability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there will be accidents involving more people. Because sometimes,
whatever your driving skills, there is no way avoinding the accident.
And at this time, someone has to take responsability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why, like i said, at first the vehicles will probably not be allowed to
be fully autonomous. Because nobody will want to take the responsability.
And by saying &amp;ldquo;nobody&amp;rdquo;, i&amp;rsquo;m thinking of the car maker. Today, their
responsability is limited to the mechanical defects of their vehicles. But
when their software will be behind the wheel,
they will be blamed for everything going wrong.
So they just won&amp;rsquo;t take the chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easy workaround here is to do like tesla did: The driver is in charge,
and the car can drive under supervision. This is the way to go at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-road-is-non-standard&#34;&gt;A road is non-standard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think cars are ready to drive on every kind of road for now,
because roads are too different from each other. Even the same road
can be different whether it&amp;rsquo;s day or night, summer or winter. City roads
are different from country roads. So a first step would be to define on
which kind of road a fully autonomous car will be competent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first step would be to define a set of requirements for the road. A set of
characteristics on which the car can count on to locate and drive itself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;signs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;borders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lanes paintings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second step will be to enhance cars artificial intelligence to handle
the other kinds of roads. I think deep learning will play a huge role on this.
Having some kind of hybrid intelligence cars: driving on deep learning, but
respecting the basic predicates of standard hazard detection and self
regulation rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-ethics&#34;&gt;The ethics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be continued&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>